{
  "reference_number": "11691",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "There have been too many delays already - lets get going - we only have 32 years from now and that's not long for making major\n changes in how we live on and view this land."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Long-Lived Gases and Stabilised Short-Lived Gases - Long-lived gases to net zero by 2050 while also stabilising short-lived gases",
      "answer_index": 12,
      "notes": "My personal preference is actually net zero emissions but with 44% of greenhouse emissions coming from agriculture, which is also\n\n still our primary industry, our target needs to be manageable and possible. This target could be adjusted to say reduced short-lived\n gases rather than stabilised."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "We need to meet this target for our own sake. My concerns are - 1. will government work with us to achieve this - e.g. could the GST\n\n be waived on electric cars on the proviso to make them available to more people and 2. how forestry is interpreted. Currently we\n seem to plant pine on any type of land without regard to terrain, soil retention or impact on waterways and downstream flooding after\n harvesting. I would like to see steep, highly erodible land returned to native forest with some areas on private land able to be\n\n selectively logged for fine timber but no clear felling. Waterways should always have WIDE buffer zones of permanent planting. We are\n the one's who need stronger environmental safeguards."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "It is important to have a strong target, Hopefully this will give both business and government the incentive to invest in innovative\n\n research."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "No - emissions budgets should not be able to be changed",
      "answer_index": 9,
      "notes": "A little bit of policy stability would be nice!"
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "But must be exceptional such as a major volcanic eruption!"
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "People need to feel supported by their government so must create clear and unambiguous guidelines and clear statements about\nwhat the government can do or not and what will be required of businesses and individuals."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "What areas will be targeted in each budget and who will be most affected? Some sector groups may already have ideas for emission\nreduction - is new research needed - Can the Commission facilitate this? New technology - any available overseas? Are there low tech\n\nsolutions? Need government, business leaders and environmental experts working together so our solutions don't create new\nproblems"
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "And must have mechanisms to hold the government to account. NZ governments have often ignored or just paid lip service to\n\nenvironmental concerns."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Makes decisions itself in respect of the number of units available in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 10,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Lot of words - sounds good but where's the action on the things we already know? e.g. Why are we still building on low-level coastal\nground? What actions will be required - e.g. to preserve essential infrastructure? The proposed risk assessment is very broad and\n\nthere doesn't seem to be any requirement for government bodies to have to take it into account in their planning?"
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "We are all involved in this matter so community engagement is really important. Besides the cities, this must include rural and small\ntowns as we are already being adversely affected by high fuel costs, a lack of public transport and high travel needs for services and\n\namenities. We need to find better ways to talk about and to support our farmers while still holding them to account environmentally.\nPlease build systems that help people stay in work and not on welfare."
    }
  ]
}
